Why can't we use
that satellite?
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
（男性１）
なんでそっちが使えないんだ？
You say it'll only take 20 or 30 minutes, but we're
the ones who are gonna take the flak for it!
たった:only/merely/but
たった20～30分とか言うけど―
それだけで ドヤされるのは
こっちなんだからな
INTO-mandated work is underway. Thank you for your cooperation.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
（管制官）こちらCD-51
This is CD-51.
I'm getting an interference warning
in our Navstar link.
ナブスター:Navstar, リンク:link/directory entry, 接続[せつぞく]:connection|changing trains|conjunction, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, 警報[けいほう]:alarm/warning, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
ナブスターとのリンク接続に
障害警報を確認
ネットワーク:network, チェック:check/plaid/checkered, 要請[ようせい]:appeal/call for something|axiom
ネットワークのチェックを要請する
Request network check.
Something wrong out there?
It's taking an awfully long time.
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 時間がかかる[じかんがかかる]:to take time
（男性２）どうした？
やけに時間がかかっているようだが
新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), ドジる:to fail/to mess up/to bungle
（作業員）すいません
ちょっと新人がドジっちまって
Sorry, our new guy botched
something up.
It won't be
much longer.
もうちょっと
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, ヘルプ:help, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of, 抜く[ぬく]:to extract|to do something to the end|to surpass||
（男性２）ヘルプだからって
気ぃ抜かないでくれよ
Just 'cause you guys are temp workers
doesn't mean you can afford to get careless.
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
（作業員）ああ 分かっています
急ぎますので
Yeah, I know.
We're working as fast as we can.
男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender, 定期検査[ていきけんさ]:periodic inspection/regular inspection
（男性２）
ただの定期検査なんだから―
This is just a regular inspection,
so make it snappy.
チャッチャとやってくれよな
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
Units 3 and 4,
report status.
（男性）ああっ…
Phase 23
Debris Cluster
Unit 3, all clear.
Unit 4, all clear.
Next, please.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, どうぞ:please/kindly|by all means
（検査員）次の方どうぞ
Due to the increase in security accompanying
the Supreme Council meeting,
最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, 開催[かいさい]:holding a meeting/opening an exhibition/hosting (e.g. the Olympics), 伴う[ともなう]:to accompany/to go hand in hand with|to be accompanied by
（アナウンス）
最高評議会開催に伴う―
警備[けいび]:defense/defence/guard, 強化[きょうか]:strengthening/intensifying/reinforcement
警備強化のため…
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, ステーション:station, 寄る[よる]:to approach|to gather (in one place)|to stop by (while on one's way to another place)||
（クレア）軌道ステーションには
寄らないんですか？
We're not going to
the lunar station?
...level 4 security protocols
are now in place.
最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, おかげ:grace (of God)/benevolence (of Buddha)|assistance
（ユーリ）
最高評議会のおかげで―
The area around the station is a madhouse
because of the Supreme Council meeting.
ステーション:station, 周辺[しゅうへん]:circumference/outskirts|(computer) peripheral, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 混雑[こんざつ]:congestion/crush|confusion
ステーション周辺は
大混雑だからね
We thank you for
your cooperation.
ドック:dock, 直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, ミッション:mission, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
ドックから
直接 ミッションに向かう
We will be flying our missions
straight out of the dock.
どちら:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives)
（警察官）どちらへ？
Where are you going?
Yuri Mihairokoh, age 37.
歳[さい]:-years-old|ability/gift, 歳[とし]:year|age|past one's prime
ユーリ･ミハイロコフ 37歳
Employed in the Debris Section
of Technora's Second Division.
社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 所属[しょぞく]:attached to/belong to/member
テクノーラ社
第２事業部 デブリ課所属
This is...
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
こちらへは…
（警察官）あの…
- Um...
You are stopping us
for questioning, yes?
職務質問[しょくむしつもん]:police questioning
職務質問ですよねえ
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||
これで５回目ですから
This is my fifth time.
Amid intense security measures, the first
extraterrestrial Supreme Council meeting...
ものものしい:strict (e.g. security)/heavy (e.g. guard)|showy, 警備[けいび]:defense/defence/guard
（リポーター）
ものものしい警備の中―
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, ステーション:station
ここ
月の軌道ステーションでは―
...is about to be held here
on the lunar orbital station.
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, 開く[ひらく]:to open|to bloom|to open (for business, e.g. in the morning)||, 開く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
地球外で初めての最高評議会が
開かれようとしています
The top item on this
session's agenda is...
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 主な[おもな]:chief/main/principal, 議題[ぎだい]:topic of discussion/agenda, 資源[しげん]:resources
今回の主な議題は
月資源についての…
フィー:phi
（ユーリ）やあ フィー
（フィー）ん？
Hello, Fee.
まいる:to go/to come|to be defeated, 回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, 止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
まいったよ
ここに来るまで ９回も止められた
This is ridiculous. We were stopped
nine times on the way here.
Do I look like such a
dangerous man to you?
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
そんなに
危ない男に見えるかなあ 俺
- Late...
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
（フィー）遅い
（ユーリ）え？
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
遅い！
You're late!
"The first off-world Supreme Council meeting,"
my ass!
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 行う[おこなう]:to perform/to do/to conduct oneself, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees
（フィー）何が
地球外で行われる初めての評議会だ
The first-world countries are just trying
to monopolize lunar resources, right?
要[かなめ]:pivot|vital point|Japanese photinia, 要[よう]:cornerstone|requirement|necessary, 先進国[せんしんこく]:advanced (developed) country/advanced nations, 資源[しげん]:resources, 独占[どくせん]:monopoly/monopolization|hogging
要は先進国で
月資源を独占しようってことだろ？
わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
わざわざ
月まで来なくたっていいのにさ
It's not like they needed to come
all the way to the moon to do that.
The political wrangling's
already over,
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 根回し[ねまわし]:making necessary arrangements/laying the groundwork|digging around the roots of a tree (before transplanting), 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, 議長[ぎちょう]:chairman/speaker (e.g. of assembly)/president (e.g. of council, senate, etc.), 案[あん]:idea|draft plan|expectation, 案[つくえ, つき]:desk, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
どうせ根回しも終わって
議長案に決まるんだから―
...and they're just gonna rubber-stamp
the Chairman's bill, anyway,
...so they shouldn't even bother with holding
a meeting, that's all I'm sayin'.
いちいち:one-by-one/separately|every single, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 開く[ひらく]:to open|to bloom|to open (for business, e.g. in the morning)||, 開く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||, っつー:meaning/called/said
もう いちいち
評議会なんて開くなっつーの
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 分担金[ぶんたんきん]:share of expenses/contribution, 応ずる[おうずる]:to answer/to respond|to satisfy, 資源[しげん]:resources, 分配[ぶんぱい]:division/splitting/sharing
連合への分担金に応じて
月資源を分配する？
Dividing up the moon's resources based
on countries' contributions to INTO?
Ha! All that means is the guys who shell out
the most money are gonna get the resources.
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal, 資源[しげん]:resources, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
ハッ 結局 金を出したやつらが
資源をもらうってことだろ？
They don't have to come
to the moon to decide that!
いちいち:one-by-one/separately|every single, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
んなこと
いちいち月に来て決めんな！
All sectors of Sea of Tranquility City
are currently on...
...a heightened state of alert due
to the Supreme Council meeting.
Feeling better now?
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||
（ユーリ）落ち着いた？
（フィー）ああ
Yeah...
I'm glad to hear it.
（ユーリ）ああ それはよかった
For details regarding
traffic control,
Very glad.
本当に
Geez, how could they make the whole
damn station a nonsmoking zone?
...please direct all questions to the Session
Committee Guidance Center or Information.
ステーション:station, 丸ごと[まるごと]:in its entirety/whole/wholly, 禁煙[きんえん]:abstaining from smoking/quitting smoking|No Smoking!, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（フィー）たーく
ステーション丸ごと禁煙なんて
喫煙所[きつえんしょ, きつえんじょ]:smoking area (corner), 爆弾[ばくだん, バクダン]:bomb|alcohol with liquor added (esp. wine-based shochu highball, also beer with whiskey), 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps), 嫌う[きらう]:to hate/to dislike/to loathe
（クレア）喫煙所に爆弾を
仕掛けられるのを嫌ったんでしょう
They were probably fed up with bombs
being planted in their smoking rooms.
They're going overboard. It looked to me
like there were more cops than civilians.
過ぎ[すぎ]:past/after|too (much)
（フィー）やり過ぎなんだよ
Access to certain portions of the
dock area is currently restricted.
一般人[いっぱんじん]:ordinary person/member of the general public/non-celebrity, 警官[けいかん]:police officer/policeman/constable
一般人より
警官のほうが多いんじゃないか？
Geez, where did they
find all those...
Persons without proper authorization
will not be allowed entry...
まったく:really/truly|indeed, 湧く[わく]:to well (up)|to appear (esp. suddenly) (sweat, tears, etc.)|to feel emotions form (joy, bravery, etc.)|
まったく
どこから湧いて… うん？
（ユーリ）うん？
Yuri, where did all of those
policemen come from?
警官[けいかん]:police officer/policeman/constable
（フィー）ユーリ あの警官たちは
どこから来たんだ？
静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm, 海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, 半数[はんすう]:half the number|haploid, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 回す[まわす]:to turn|to circulate|to surround||
月だよ 静(しず)かの海(うみ)からも
半数近く 回してるって
The moon. They say that even Tranquility City
has sent nearly half their police force there.
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly
（フィー）ふーん
Sorry, guys, but go on ahead
to the dock without me.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), ドック:dock
悪いけど 先にドックへ行ってくれ
用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|
私は ちょっと
やぼ用を済ませてから行く
I'll meet you there after I see to something.
（クレア）ああ…
（ユーリ）うん？
本船[ほんせん]:mother ship/this ship, 秒[びょう]:second (60th min), 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 補助[ほじょ]:assistance|subsidy|auxiliary|, エンジン:engine, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person
（アナウンス）本船は 90秒後より
補助エンジンを停止し―
Auxiliary engines will shut down
in 90 seconds,
...and the ship will begin
circumlunar orbit test.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 周回[しゅうかい]:going around/orbiting|circumference, テスト:test, 移行[いこう]:switching over to/migration/transition
月軌道周回テストに移行する
状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
（ハチマキ）
状況の確認に来ました
I'm here to get confirmation
on our status.
All hands, report to your
designated stations.
問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
（ゴロー）
ああ？ ああ 問題ない
Oh, everything looks good.
顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
ああ… ひでえ顔だな おい
You look like hell, boy.
You need to lose some of that
tension in your shoulders.
肩[かた]:shoulder, 抜ける[ぬける]:to come out|to fade|to wear a hole (e.g. clothes)||
ちったあ 肩の力 抜けよ
Find a girl or go down to Earth.
Just do something.
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 降りる[おりる]:to descend (e.g. a mountain)|to alight (e.g. from bus)|to step down||
女に会うとか 地球に降りるとかさ
実家[じっか]:(one's parents') home, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 母ちゃん[かあちゃん]:mum/mom, トンカツ:tonkatsu/breaded pork cutlet, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
実家に帰って
母ちゃんのトンカツ食えば―
Go on home and eat some of your
mother's pork cutlets, and you'll feel...
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 発[はつ]:departure|sending|engine||, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
一発で…
（ハチマキ）先生が…
- It's Sensei...
（ハチマキ）死んだ
He's dead.
ギガルトが？
Gigalt's dead?
It was cancer. Radiation got him.
放射線[ほうしゃせん]:radiation
ガンだ 放射線にやられたって
（ゴロー）ああっ…
He is?
そうか
あいつが…
He's really dead...
I've got a really bad feeling
about this.
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant, 予感[よかん]:presentiment/premonition|to have a premonition
（フィー）
なんか とても嫌な予感がするの
静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm, 警備[けいび]:defense/defence/guard, 薄い[うすい]:thin|pale|watery||
今 静かの海市の
警備が薄くなってる
Security in Tranquility City
is really thin right now.
戦力[せんりょく]:war potential/military strength|ability (to compete), 簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief, 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps), ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
やつらの戦力でも
簡単に仕掛けられるぐらいにね
Thin enough that they could easily launch
an attack, even with a force their size.
Attacking the Von Braun or
Doctor Locksmith would be one thing,
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 博士[はかせ, はくし]:doctorate/PhD|expert, ともかく:anyhow/anyway/somehow or other
（ドルフ）フォン･ブラウン号や
ロックスミス博士ならともかく―
程度[ていど]:degree/amount/grade, 狙う[ねらう]:to aim at, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
私程度を狙ったところで
意味はないぞ
...but there's little point in targeting
someone as inconsequential as me.
You think so?
（フィー）そう？
You're the one who needs
to be careful.
気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
君こそ 気をつけたほうがいい
You and your people foiled
one of their plans before.
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations, 阻止[そし]:obstruction/check/hindrance
君たちは一度
彼らの作戦を阻止してるし
I guess we've got some kind of
connection with those guys...
縁がある[えんがある]:to be fated to/be linked by fate
なーんか 縁があるんだよねえ
あいつらとは
Well, never mind. Sorry I bothered you.
邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
まあ いいや 邪魔したね
要件[ようけん]:important matter|requirement/requisite
要件は それだけか？
Was that all you were
calling about?
What, is there something
strange about that?
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
（フィー）ええっ？ おかしい？
うっ ああ…
フィー:phi, 今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
フィー よかったら 今度…
Fee. Why don't
you and l...
What's the problem here?
（フィー）何？
Yeah?
Something about repairs on
the emergency generator.
旦那[だんな]:master (of a house, shop, etc.)|husband (informal)|sir||, よろしく:well/properly|best regards
（ドルフ）ああ いや
旦那とアルによろしく
Forget it. Give my regards
to your husband and Al.
Repairs? I don't remember putting
in a request for repairs.
Sure. I'll tell them that their favorite
old geezer with the big forehead says hi.
伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
ああ デコのおっちゃんが
そう言ってたと伝えとくよ じゃ
No, that can't be right.
For disaster prevention?
'Bye.
Anyway, we haven't heard anything
about this from the building owner.
（チャド）にしても―
オーナー:owner, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
ビルのオーナーからは
何も連絡をもらっていない
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
（作業員）とにかく急ぎますので
入らせていただきます
We're in a hurry, sir, so we're
going to let ourselves in.
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily
（チャド）こら 君 勝手に…
Hey! I didn't say
you could come in!
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 依頼[いらい]:request/commission|dependence, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||
（作業員）こちらも
依頼を受けて来ているもんで
We were asked to come here
and do this work.
Like I said, we haven't put in a request
for work on the emergency generator!
非常[ひじょう]:emergency|extraordinary/unusual, 電源[でんげん]:source of electricity/electrical power|power (button on TV, etc.), 工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（チャド）
だから 非常電源の工事なんて―
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
頼んでないって言っただろ
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, ガリレオ:Galileo, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 発注[はっちゅう]:ordering (materials)/placing an order/order
（作業員）でも 確かに
ガリレオ開発の発注なんですよ
But I'm positive that the request
was from Galileo Development...
担当者[たんとうしゃ]:person in charge (of an area of work, but not necessarily supervising other staff)/person responsible/one in charge
（ドルフ）担当者は？
Who's in charge here?
Could you show me the work order?
発注[はっちゅう]:ordering (materials)/placing an order/order, 書[ふみ]:letter/writings, 見せる[みせる]:to show/to display, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
発注書を見せてもらえば
You must be President Dolf.
社長[しゃちょう]:company president/manager/director
（作業員）ドルフ社長ですね？
（ドルフ）うん？
（ドルフ）うっ…
（チャド）あっ
（ドルフ）うっ… う うう…
（チャド）ドルフ
Dolf!
（社員）ああっ…
Somebody call an ambulance!
救急[きゅうきゅう]:first-aid/emergency (aid), センター:centre/center
誰か！ 救急センターに…
- Be quiet!
静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm
（コートの男）静かにしろ！
黙る[だまる]:to be silent, 従える[したがえる]:to be accompanied by|to conquer/to subjugate
（コートの男）いいか 黙って従え
Okay, just shut up
and do as you're told.
逆らう[さからう]:to go against/to oppose/to disobey, 撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat
逆らうものは 撃つ
Anyone who disobeys
will be shot.
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures
（コリン）ちょうどよかったよ
Boy, am I glad
to see you!
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 視察[しさつ]:inspection/observation, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
フォン･ブラウン号の
視察なんて―
All this inspection work on the
Von Braun is one big hassle.
面倒[めんどう]:trouble|trouble|care
面倒なだけでさ
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, 女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl
ほんと
女の子が２人も来てくれてさあ
Having two girls along
will make it...
監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement, 官[かん]:government service/the bureaucracy, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device)
（乗務員）クリフォード監査官
お電話が入っております
Inspector Clifford, there
is a phone call for you.
Would you please come to
the communications room?
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar, 越す[こす]:to cross over (e.g. mountain)|to go over (e.g. with audience)|to pass time (e.g. a winter)||, いただける:to be able to receive/to be able to take|to be able to eat
通信室まで
お越しいただけますか？
面倒くさい[めんどくさい, めんどうくさい]:bothersome/tiresome/bother to do
（コリン）ああ？ 面倒くさいなあ
What a pain...
I'm sorry, I'll be right back.
行ってくる[いってくる]:I'm off/see you later|to go (and then come back)
ごめんね ちょっと行ってくる
That's fine,
take your time.
ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful
（リュシー）はい ごゆっくり
用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
ああ でも 用が終わったら
すぐ帰ってきてね
Oh, but once you're done,
hurry back, okay?
（コリン）アハッ そうする
I'll do that.
うーん:hmm/well, 素直[すなお]:obedient/meek|honest, よろしい:good/OK/all right
うーん 素直で よろしい
It's nice when they do as they're told.
Right, Tanabe?
ねっ タナベ
元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy, 出し[だし, ダシ]:dashi (Japanese soup stock made from fish and kelp)|pretext/excuse
おい 元気 出しなって
Hey, cheer up.
（タナベ）うん
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, ばっか:only/merely|approximately
きっと
自分の先生が死んだばっかで―
I bet he was just upset because
his Sensei had just died.
気が立つ[きがたつ]:to be excited about/to get all worked up about
気が立ってたんだよ
（タナベ）うん
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, ステーション:station, 寄る[よる]:to approach|to gather (in one place)|to stop by (while on one's way to another place)||
（クレア）
軌道ステーションには寄らずに―
We'll be flying straight to the mission area
without going to the orbital station first.
ミッション:mission, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, 都合[つごう]:circumstances|to arrange|to lend money|
このまま ミッションに向かうって
評議会の都合で
It's due to the Supreme Council meeting.
（ユーリ）クレア
（クレア）はっ
Claire.
I heard that there was a request to
carry some extra cargo. Is that it?
積み荷[つみに]:load/freight/cargo, 追加[ついか]:addition/supplement/append (e.g. to a file), 申請[しんせい]:application/request/petition
（ユーリ）積み荷の追加申請が
あるって聞いたんだけど それ？
Yes.
（クレア）はい
Where is it from? Why would someone
send an airtight case?
物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（ユーリ）どこからの物？
エアタイトケースなんて
I don't know.
Tanabe-san isn't here, so l...
さんがい:the three realms of existence|the whole universe (of a billion worlds) that Buddha enlightened, さんがい:third floor
（クレア）さあ…
タナベさんがいないので
Tanabe?
タナベが…
甘い[あまい]:sweet-tasting|fragrant (smelling)|lightly salted||, 甘い[うまい]:skillful|delicious|fortunate
甘いと思っている？
You think that we were
too soft on her?
（クレア）えっ？
For letting Tanabe go to
the Von Braun, I mean.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
タナベを
フォン･ブラウン号に行かせたこと
No.
（クレア）いえ
ハチマキ:headband, 突然[とつぜん]:abrupt/sudden/unexpected, 会社を辞める[かいしゃをやめる]:to leave the company
ハチマキが 突然
会社を辞めると言いだしたとき―
When Hachimaki told us out of the blue
that he was quitting the company,
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, ひどい:cruel/heartless|violent, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation
とてもひどい状態でね
...he was in a
terrible state.
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be, 感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression
誰の言うことも
聞こえないって感じで―
It was as if he was deaf
to everyone around him.
周り[まわり]:circumference/girth|surroundings, 対する[たいする]:to face (each other)|to be directed toward (the future, etc.)|to receive (a client, etc.)||, 壁[かべ, へき]:wall|barrier|Chinese "Wall" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
周りに対して壁を作ってしまう
自分では壊せない壁を
He has built a wall around himself.
A wall that he can't break on his own.
分かるんだ
自分も そうだったから
I can tell.
I once did the same thing.
ムチャクチャ:nonsensical/unreasonable/absurd, パワー:power
けど タナベの
ムチャクチャなパワーなら―
But with that crazy power of hers, we thought
that Tanabe might be able to smash it down.
壁[かべ, へき]:wall|barrier|Chinese "Wall" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
その壁を壊せるんじゃないかって
なさる:to do
（クレア）ごめんなさい 私には…
I'm sorry, I didn't know.
出発時刻[しゅっぱつじこく]:departure time/flight time, 後ろ[うしろ]:back/behind/rear, ずらす:to shift/to slide (e.g. something away from something else)|to put off
（管制官）CS-27
出発時刻を１時間後ろにずらします
CS-27, I'm moving your
departure time back by an hour.
Repeating, CS-27, I'm moving your
繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again, 出発時刻[しゅっぱつじこく]:departure time/flight time, ずらす:to shift/to slide (e.g. something away from something else)|to put off
繰り返します CS-27
出発時刻を１時間ずらします
What's the meaning
of this?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
（チェンシン）
どういうことですか？
Our own DS-12 is already flying
along your launch trajectory.
発信[はっしん]:dispatch/despatch/transmission, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 既に[すでに, すんでに]:already/too late, 我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, 侵入[しんにゅう]:invasion/incursion/raid, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
（管制官）発信軌道上には既に
我が社のDS-12が侵入しています
Why are our courses butting up against
each other? We're in the same company!
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, バッティング:batting
（チェンシン）どうして 軌道が
バッティングしてるんですか？
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
それも同じ会社で
Communication error.
連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|
（管制官）連絡ミスです
They took off straight from
the moon's surface.
向こう[むこう]:opposite side|over there|the other party|, 月面[げつめん]:moon's surface, 直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, 発進[はっしん]:departure/takeoff
向こうは
月面から直接 発進しました
I'll contact you again in an hour.
You copy?
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|
１時間後に また ご連絡します
コピー:copy/photocopy
ユー コピー？
I copy...
コピー:copy/photocopy
アイ コピー
DS-12…
The DS-12... We're playing second fiddle
to a debris hauler, huh?
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 後回し[あとまわし]:putting off/postponing
デブリ回収船より後回しか
Don't let it
get you down.
腐る[くさる]:to rot|to corrode|to become useless||
（操縦士）腐るなよ
A guy like you will make it back
to passenger liners in no time.
客船[きゃくせん]:passenger boat, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
君ならそのうち 客船に戻れるさ
Stop trying to make
me feel better.
気休め[きやすめ]:mere consolation/temporary peace of mind, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
気休めは やめてください
I'm going to go do
a cargo check.
カーゴ:cargo, チェック:check/plaid/checkered, してき:historic/historical, してき:pointing out/identification
カーゴのチェックをしてきます
ぼんやり:dimly/faintly|absentmindedly, もったい:superior airs/air of importance|overemphasis
ぼんやりしてるだけじゃ
時間がもったいないですから
Sitting around doing nothing will
make this extra time go to waste.
What's his problem?
（操縦士）なんだかな
I hereby proclaim that the 13th meeting of
the INTO Supreme Council is in session.
（クリフォード）
それでは ここに―
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, 開催[かいさい]:holding a meeting/opening an exhibition/hosting (e.g. the Olympics), 宣言[せんげん]:declaration/proclamation/announcement
第13回 連合最高評議会の
開催を宣言します
This first Supreme Council meeting held off
of the Earth has great political significance,
史上[しじょう]:in history/ever/historical, 初[はつ, うい]:first/new, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, 開催[かいさい]:holding a meeting/opening an exhibition/hosting (e.g. the Olympics)
（アナウンサー）史上初
地球外での最高評議会の開催は―
政治的[せいじてき]:political, 意味合い[いみあい]:implication/nuance/shade of meaning, もとより:from the beginning/from the first|of course
政治的な意味合いはもとより―
技術[ぎじゅつ]:technology|technique|art, 発展[はってん]:development|expansion|playing around, 開く[ひらく]:to open|to bloom|to open (for business, e.g. in the morning)||, 開く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||, 新天地[しんてんち]:new land/new world/new sphere of activity
技術の発展により
開かれた新天地で―
...and is also a symbolic act in which
leaders of the world's nations...
各国[かっこく, かくこく]:each nation|many nations/many countries, 首脳[しゅのう]:head/leader|important part, 一堂に会する[いちどうにかいする]:to assemble (in a hall)/to meet together (in a room), 象徴的[しょうちょうてき]:symbolic, 出来事[できごと, できこと]:incident/affair/happening, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
各国の首脳が一堂に会するという
象徴的な出来事でもあり―
...are all meeting in a new frontier that was
opened up by technological advances.
Regardless of the meeting's focus, the division
and administration of the lunar surface,
焦点[しょうてん]:focus (e.g. photographic)/focal point, 月面[げつめん]:moon's surface, 分割[ぶんかつ]:partition/division/separation, 分割[ぶわり]:rate/ratio|commission, 管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business), 是非[ぜひ]:certainly/without fail|right and wrong, 以前[いぜん]:ago/since/before
焦点となっている
月面の分割管理の是非以前に―
...many say that there is deep significance
in the announcement of the meeting itself.
開催[かいさい]:holding a meeting/opening an exhibition/hosting (e.g. the Olympics), 宣言[せんげん]:declaration/proclamation/announcement, 自体[じたい]:itself|one's own body|originally, 意味がある[いみがある]:to have meaning/to be meaningful, 声[こえ]:voice
開催が宣言されたこと自体に
意味があるとの声も―
大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, きてい:base/ground|basis, きてい:default/established/pre-arranged
大きくなってきています
始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from)
（コートの男）よし 始まったぞ
Okay, it's started.
Almost ready here.
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room
（組織員１）こちらも間もなく
来た
Got it.
Okay, wake him up.
そいつ:he/she|that, 起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||
（コートの男）
よし そいつを起こせ
Hey! Get up, damn it!
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, 起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents)
（組織員２）
おい！ この 起きろよ
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, データ:data/datum, 集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather, きれる:to break/to snap|to be injured, きれる:to be able to wear/to fit into
（コートの男）
悪いね あんたのデータだけは
集めきれなかったからな
Sorry about this.
We could get everyone's data but yours.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, データ:data/datum, 集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather, きれる:to break/to snap|to be injured, きれる:to be able to wear/to fit into
（コートの男）
悪いね あんたのデータだけは
集めきれなかったからな
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, 面倒[めんどう]:trouble|trouble|care, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
（組織員２）ほら
面倒かけんじゃねえよ
- Don't make any trouble!
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, 面倒[めんどう]:trouble|trouble|care, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
（組織員２）ほら
面倒かけんじゃねえよ
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, 面倒[めんどう]:trouble|trouble|care, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
（組織員２）ほら
面倒かけんじゃねえよ
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（チャド）
やめろ！ ケガしてるんだぞ
- Stop it, he's hurt!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（チャド）
やめろ！ ケガしてるんだぞ
あっ うっ うう…
Do it!
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member
（組織員２）さあ！
Open your eyes!
開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
目を開けろよ
（ドルフ）うっ…
We don't have time for this.
Don't make things difficult.
手間をかける[てまをかける]:to take up someone's time/to make work for someone, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
（コートの男）
時間がない 手間をかけさせるな
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member
（ドルフ）うっ…
（組織員１）んんん…
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 網膜[もうまく]:retina, 照合[しょうごう]:collation/comparison
（組織員２）
駄目です 網膜を照合できません
It's no use. I can't
get a retinal match.
（チャド）ううっ うう…
死人[しにん, しびと]:corpse/dead person, なるべく:as much as possible/wherever practicable
（コートの男）
死人はなるべく出したくないが―
I'd prefer to keep the casualties
to a minimum,
...but that will depend on
how cooperative you are.
協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration, しだい:depending on|as soon as/immediately (upon), しだい:private university or college
君の協力しだいでは どうなるか…
Understand?
分かるよな
（チャド）ううっ… ううっ
What'll it be?
（コートの男）どうする？
If you guarantee the
safety of my people.
皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 保障[ほしょう]:guarantee/security/assurance
皆の安全を保障するなら
Of course.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally
（コートの男）もちろん
おい
Hey.
（ドルフ）ううっ…
The system's open.
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, システム:system, 開く[ひらく]:to open|to bloom|to open (for business, e.g. in the morning)||, 開く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||
（組織員１）システム 開きました
送信[そうしん]:transmission/sending
（コートの男）よし 送信しろ
Okay, send the signal.
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member
（組織員１）はい
Right.
マタタビ:silver vine (Actinidia polygama)/cat powder, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure, 黒猫[くろねこ, くろネコ]:black cat, カバン:bag/satchel/briefcase, 渡す[わたす]:to ferry across (e.g. a river)|to lay across|to hand over
マタタビは手に入れた
黒猫にカバンを渡せ
We have the catnip.
Pass the bag to Black Cat.
（ドルフ）ううっ
KC-35, KC-35, you have crossed
into our orbit. Please respond.
（フィー）KC-35 KC-35
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 進路[しんろ]:route/course|one's future course (e.g. after graduating high school), 侵入[しんにゅう]:invasion/incursion/raid, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, 応答[おうとう]:reply/answer/response
貴船は こちらの進路に
侵入しています 応答せよ
Control, KC-35 is flying on
our trajectory. What's going on?
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 進路[しんろ]:route/course|one's future course (e.g. after graduating high school)
管制課 こちらの進路に
KC-35が入ってるが―
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
どういうことだ？
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), コール:(telephone) call/(telephone) ring, 繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again
（管制官）こちらも
コールを繰り返しているが―
We've been trying to hail them,
too, but there's no response.
応答[おうとう]:reply/answer/response
応答がない
フィー:phi
（ユーリ）どうした？ フィー
What's up, Fee?
There's something fishy
about that ship up ahead.
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 様子[ようす]:state|appearance|sign, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
前の船 様子がおかしい
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 交信[こうしん]:telecommunications/correspondence
管制課のほうでも
交信ができないって言うし
Control says that they can't establish
contact with them, either.
The Space Defense Front?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
（ユーリ）宇宙防衛戦線？
Maybe.
（フィー）かもね
接近[せっきん]:getting closer|being not much different|becoming close (i.e. friendly), フィッシュ:fish, ボーン:born, 準備[じゅんび]:preparation/setup/arrangements, よろしく:well/properly|best regards
接近するよ
フィッシュボーンの準備 よろしく
I'll take us in closer.
Get the Fishbone ready for launch.
I copy.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ユーリ）アイ コピー
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
クレア 聞こえる？
Claire, do you hear me? We've got a
situation here. Go with Yuri, and...
緊急事態[きんきゅうじたい]:state of emergency, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
緊急事態だ ユーリと一緒に…
（殴る音）
（ユーリ）うっ
Hold it right there.
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
（クレア）動かないで
（フィー）はっ
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
クレア？
（クレア）この船は―
Claire?
We're commandeering this ship in the
name of the Space Defense Front.
我々[われわれ]:we, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 徴用[ちょうよう]:drafting/requisition/impressment
我々 宇宙防衛戦線が徴用する
（フィー）あっ ユーリ！
Yuri!
この…
You sons of...
If you offer any resistance...
抵抗[ていこう]:resistance|reluctance|resistance||
（クレア）抵抗すれば―
撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat
撃ちます
I'll shoot you.
応答[おうとう]:reply/answer/response
（管制官）DS-12 DS-12 応答せよ
DS-12. DS-12, respond.
You are out of your scheduled orbit.
予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 外れる[はずれる]:to be disconnected/to get out of place/to be off
予定軌道を外れています
DS-12, correct your
course immediately.
直ちに[ただちに]:at once/immediately/directly, 航路[こうろ]:(air or sea) route/course/line, 修正[しゅうせい]:amendment/correction/revision, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
DS-12は
直ちに航路を修正してください
We are sending you your orbital data,
so establish a Navstar link.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, データ:data/datum, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||, ナブスター:Navstar, 接続[せつぞく]:connection|changing trains|conjunction
軌道データを送りますので
ナブスターとの接続を…
DS-12?
DS-12
Come in, DS-12. DS-12!
応答[おうとう]:reply/answer/response
（管制官）
応答せよ DS-12 DS-12
（男性）おい こら
Hey!
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 持ち場[もちば]:job/station/position, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|
（男性）勝手に持ち場を離れんな
Don't leave your post!
How are we gonna relay our broadcast now?!
番組[ばんぐみ]:program (e.g. TV)/programme, 中継[ちゅうけい]:relay/hook-up|relay broadcasting, 中継[なかつぎ]:joining/joint|mid-relief pitcher
番組の中継はどうすんだよ
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
（管制官）DA-47 聞こえますか？
DA-47, do you read?
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
DA-47 聞こえますか？
DA-47, do you read?
応答[おうとう]:reply/answer/response, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, ナブスター:Navstar
応答してください
ナブスターとの…
Please respond. I'm showing a
Navstar disconnect alarm here.
（指揮官）どうした？
What's going on?
We're getting interference across the public
comm channels. It's covering all of lunar orbit.
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 一般[いっぱん]:general/universal|ordinary, 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, チャンネル:channel, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, 発生[はっせい]:outbreak|generation (e.g. of power or heat)|ontogeny
（管制官１）
一般通信チャンネルに障害発生
範囲[はんい]:extent/scope/sphere, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 一帯[いったい]:region/zone/whole place, 多元[たげん]:pluralism/diversity, 位相[いそう]:phase (e.g. wave, electricity, moon)|topology|register, 干渉[かんしょう]:interference/intervention/meddling
範囲は月軌道一帯
多元位相干渉と思われます
It looks like multi-phasic
interference.
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 報告[ほうこく]:report/information
（管制官２）
テクノーラ社より報告
Report from Technora.
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, 航路[こうろ]:(air or sea) route/course/line, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|
デブリ回収船 DS-12が
予定航路を離れました
Debris recovery ship DS-12 is out of
its planned flight path.
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), テレビ:television/TV
（管制官３）
セレーネ･テレビから…
Selena TV reports that news
ship PV-12 isn't responding.
- What about INTO comm channels?
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, チャンネル:channel
連合の通信チャンネルは？
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 稼働率[かどうりつ]:operating ratio/rate of operation/availability factor, パーセント:percent/percentage, 低下[ていか]:fall/decline/lowering
（管制官４）
稼働率64パーセントまで低下
Rate of operation is down to 64%.
Interference area is spreading.
障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, 範囲[はんい]:extent/scope/sphere, 広がる[ひろがる]:to spread (out)/to extend/to stretch
障害範囲 広がりつつあります
Many factors are involved in development.
- Chairman Clifford.
議長[ぎちょう]:chairman/speaker (e.g. of assembly)/president (e.g. of council, senate, etc.), 失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
（秘書）クリフォード議長
（クリフォード）失礼
Excuse me.
Six civilian ships near lunar orbit have gone
silent and have left their scheduled orbits.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 付近[ふきん]:neighbourhood/neighborhood|approaching, 民間[みんかん]:private/civilian/civil, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 隻[せき]:counter for ships (large boats)|counter for half of a pair (e.g. half of a folding screen)|counter for fish, birds, arrows, etc.
（秘書）
月軌道付近の民間船６隻が―
一斉[いっせい]:simultaneous/all at once, 交信[こうしん]:telecommunications/correspondence, 絶つ[たつ]:to sever|to suppress|to abstain (from), 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 外れる[はずれる]:to be disconnected/to get out of place/to be off
一斉に交信を絶って
予定軌道を外れました
So, they're launching an attack.
It's the Space Defense Front...
やはり:too/also|still, 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps), 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
やはり 仕掛けてきたか
宇宙防衛戦線
目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
（秘書）目標は
フォン･ブラウン号と思われます
We believe their target to be the Von Braun.
Let's send more patrol ships...
巡視船[じゅんしせん]:patrol boat, 増員[ぞういん]:increase the number of personnel
巡視船を増員しましょう
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
（クリフォード）動くな
（秘書）は？
Don't do anything.
Sir?
プライオリティー:priority, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
（クリフォード）
プライオリティーを考えろ
Keep your priorities
straight.
We can always build another spaceship, but
the members of this council can't be replaced.
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 造る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 我々[われわれ]:we, 代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ...
宇宙船は また造れる
だが 我々の代わりはいない
Yes, sir.
（秘書）はい
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
（クリフォード）
フォン･ブラウン号には―
The Von Braun has its
tandem mirror engine.
タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, エンジン:engine
タンデムミラーエンジンがある
自力[じりき, じりょく]:one's own strength/one's own efforts|self-salvation, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
いざとなれば
自力で逃げられるはずだ
If push comes to shove, they should
be able to get away on their own.
I'm more worried about those
six civilian ships.
気になる[きになる]:to be on one's mind|to feel like|to fancy, 隻[せき]:counter for ships (large boats)|counter for half of a pair (e.g. half of a folding screen)|counter for fish, birds, arrows, etc., 民間[みんかん]:private/civilian/civil, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
それより気になるのは
６隻の民間船だ
セオリー:theory, 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, 起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents), 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
セオリーなら
通信障害が起きてから動くだろう
In theory, the SDF should make its move
after interfering with our communications.
Could it be
a bluff, sir?
陽動[ようどう]:diversion (action meant to attract attention away from the real objective)/feint
（秘書）陽動でしょうか
話せる[はなせる]:to be able to speak/to be able to talk|to be understanding
（秘書）いい 話せ
（男性）はっ
It's all right. Report.
Yes, sir.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 電磁[でんじ]:electromagnetic, 放射[ほうしゃ]:radiation/emission, 反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response, 隻[せき]:counter for ships (large boats)|counter for half of a pair (e.g. half of a folding screen)|counter for fish, birds, arrows, etc., 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
（男性）クレメンタイン軌道に
電磁放射反応 ６隻 確認しました
We've picked up six
EM radiation sources in Clementine orbit.
We don't have any
details on them,
詳細[しょうさい]:detail/particulars, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance
詳細は不明ですが―
...but there are no registered ships
in Clementine orbit at this time.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 船舶[せんぱく]:ship
この時間にクレメンタイン軌道に
存在する船舶は―
登録[とうろく]:registration/accession/register
登録されていません
うーん:hmm/well
（クリフォード）
うーん… クレメンタインか
Clementine, huh?
先手を打つ[せんてをうつ]:to forestall/to beat to the punch|to play the first move (e.g. in go)
先手を打てるな
We can get the drop on them...
This is an emergency
transmission.
緊急[きんきゅう]:urgency/emergency, 通達[つうたつ, つうだつ]:notification/official notice|being well versed (in something)
（管制官）緊急通達
Orders for Cresta 28, Arachne 16,
and Scorpion 04 follow.
スコーピオン:scorpion, 指令[しれい]:orders/instructions/directive
クレスタ28 アラクネ16
スコーピオン05に指令
All ships, change orbit
at maximum speed.
各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 最大[さいだい]:biggest/greatest/largest, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 移行[いこう]:switching over to/migration/transition
各船 最大船速で軌道移行
Apprehend unidentified vessels
in Clementine orbit.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 捕獲[ほかく]:capture/seizure
クレメンタイン軌道上の
正体不明船を捕獲せよ
Your targets are the unidentified
vessels in Clementine orbit.
目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
目標はクレメンタイン軌道上の
正体不明船
状況による[じょうきょうによる]:depending on the situation/depending on the circumstances, 直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, 攻撃[こうげき]:attack/strike|criticism, 許可[きょか]:permission/approval|to permit, コード:code
なお 状況により
直接攻撃を許可する コードＢ…
Furthermore, you are authorized to engage
if the situation warrants it.
Follow Code B protocols...
It's no use.
Communications are down.
乗組員[のりくみいん]:crew, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 交信[こうしん]:telecommunications/correspondence, 不能[ふのう]:impossible|incompetence|impotence|
（乗組員１）
駄目です 交信不能になりました
So is our Navstar connection.
乗組員[のりくみいん]:crew, ナブスター:Navstar, 連携[れんけい]:cooperation/coordination/link
（乗組員１）
ナブスターとの連携も…
エンジン:engine, 始動[しどう]:starting (in machines)/activation
（ロックスミス）エンジン始動
（乗組員たち）ええっ？
Start the engine.
This communications interference
is obviously manmade.
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, 明らか[あきらか]:obvious/evident/clear, 人為的[じんいてき]:artificial/unnatural
（ロックスミス）この通信障害は
明らかに人為的なものだよ
The Space Defense Front, sir?
乗組員[のりくみいん]:crew, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
（乗組員２）宇宙防衛戦線…
Most likely.
恐らく[おそらく]:perhaps/likely/probably
恐らく
Wouldn't their target be the station that's
hosting the Supreme Council meeting?
乗組員[のりくみいん]:crew, 標的[ひょうてき]:target, 会議[かいぎ]:meeting/conference/session, ステーション:station
（乗組員２）
標的は会議中のステーションでは？
It's possible, but we should
get clear just to be safe.
しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away, 確実[かくじつ]:certainty/reliability/soundness
（ロックスミス）かもしれないけど
逃げといたほうが確実でしょう
乗組員[のりくみいん]:crew
（乗組員１）しかし―
But we can't start up the tandem mirror engine
without authorization from INTO, sir.
タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, エンジン:engine, 始動[しどう]:starting (in machines)/activation, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 許可[きょか]:permission/approval|to permit, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
タンデムミラーエンジンの始動には
連合の許可を取らないと
Even when communications are out?
Don't worry, I'll take full responsibility.
交信[こうしん]:telecommunications/correspondence, 不能[ふのう]:impossible|incompetence|impotence|
交信不能なのに？
責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
いいよ 私が責任 取るからさ
Stand by for engine startup.
Preparing to enter transfer orbit.
本船[ほんせん]:mother ship/this ship
（アナウンス）本船は―
エンジン:engine, 始動[しどう]:starting (in machines)/activation, 遷移[せんい]:transition, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track
これよりエンジンを始動
遷移軌道に入ります
All hands, take anti-G precautions
and brace for acceleration.
各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 乗員[じょういん]:crew, 対[たい]:opposite|versus|to (e.g. "winning a game five to three")||, 対[つい]:pair|antithesis|counter for items that come in pairs|, 防御[ぼうぎょ]:defense/defence/safeguard, 態勢[たいせい]:attitude/posture/preparedness, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, 発進[はっしん]:departure/takeoff, 備える[そなえる]:to furnish|to have ready|to possess (all that is needed)|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
各乗員は対Ｇ防御態勢を取り
発進に備えてください
That's strange. We aren't supposed to do a
flyby for the Supreme Council meeting yet.
各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 乗員[じょういん]:crew, 対[たい]:opposite|versus|to (e.g. "winning a game five to three")||, 対[つい]:pair|antithesis|counter for items that come in pairs|, 防御[ぼうぎょ]:defense/defence/safeguard, 態勢[たいせい]:attitude/posture/preparedness, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, 発進[はっしん]:departure/takeoff, 備える[そなえる]:to furnish|to have ready|to possess (all that is needed)|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
各乗員は対Ｇ防御態勢を取り
発進に備えてください
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
おかしいな
評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees, 顔見せ[かおみせ]:making one's debut|(just) showing one's face|introductory kabuki performance (to introduce the actors)|
評議会での顔見せは
まだだけど
操縦士[そうじゅうし]:pilot, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 到着[とうちゃく]:arrival
（操縦士１）あと５分で
クレメンタイン軌道に到着します
T minus 5 minutes
to Clementine orbit.
We'll be able to pick up the targets
on our optical cameras momentarily.
操縦士[そうじゅうし]:pilot, 目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 光学[こうがく]:optics, カメラ:camera, 捉える[とらえる]:to catch|to grasp (e.g. meaning)|to captivate
（操縦士２）目標 間もなく
光学カメラで捉えます
総員[そういん]:the entire strength/all hands/all the members, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 戦闘[せんとう]:battle/fight/combat, 配備[はいび]:deploy/deployment, 移行[いこう]:switching over to/migration/transition
（船長）
総員 第１次戦闘配備に移行
All hands, go to red alert.
兵装[へいそう]:armament/soldier's equipment, 安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 解除[かいじょ]:cancellation/rescinding/release, 対[たい]:opposite|versus|to (e.g. "winning a game five to three")||, 対[つい]:pair|antithesis|counter for items that come in pairs|, 艦船[かんせん]:(ocean) vessels/warship, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
兵装の安全解除 対艦船用意
Release safeties on all weapons.
Prepare for ship-to-ship combat.
Roger. Switching to ship-to-ship
combat configuration.
操縦士[そうじゅうし]:pilot, 了解[りょうかい]:comprehension/consent/understanding, 対[たい]:opposite|versus|to (e.g. "winning a game five to three")||, 対[つい]:pair|antithesis|counter for items that come in pairs|, 艦船[かんせん]:(ocean) vessels/warship, 形態[けいたい]:form/shape/figure, 移行[いこう]:switching over to/migration/transition
（操縦士３）
了解 対艦船形態に移行
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 出発[しゅっぱつ]:departure, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, 時刻[じこく]:instant/time/moment
（チェンシン）
間もなく出発予定時刻です
It's almost time
for our launch.
We're still not getting any instructions.
Was there supposed to be a flare today?
相変わらず[あいかわらず]:as ever/as usual/the same, 指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions
（操縦士）
相変わらず指示がないな
フレア:flare
フレア 出てたっけか
There's no mention of one
in the space weather report.
天象[てんしょう]:weather/astronomical phenomena, 予報[よほう]:forecast/prediction
天象予報では何も
Communications interference is at level C.
What should we do?
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, レベル:level/standard/amount
通信障害はレベルＣ どうします？
キャンセル:cancellation, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 準備[じゅんび]:preparation/setup/arrangements
キャンセルがない以上
準備だけでもしとくか
We haven't gotten a cancel order, so let's
go ahead and at least prep for launch.
We've pinpointed the source
of the comm interference.
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, 発生源[はっせいげん]:source/origin, 特定[とくてい]:specific/particular|specifying
（管制官１）通信障害の発生源が
特定できました
It's the Navstar
at Lagrange 1.
ナブスター:Navstar
ラグランジュ１のナブスターです
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, 遠隔操作[えんかくそうさ]:remote control/remote operation, 奪還[だっかん]:recovery/rescue/recapture, 困難[こんなん]:difficulty/hardship/trouble
（管制官２）機能障害のため
遠隔操作による奪還は困難
Retrieval via remote control will be
difficult due to decreased functionality.
Physical contact
will be needed.
物理的[ぶつりてき]:physical, 接触[せっしょく]:touch/contact, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
物理的接触が必要です
Send the special
response team!
特別[とくべつ]:special, 処理[しょり]:processing/dealing with/treatment, 班[はん]:group/party|squad, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 了解[りょうかい]:comprehension/consent/understanding
特別処理班を向かわせろ
（管制官３）了解
Yes, sir.
Tandem mirror engine
has reached critical.
タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, エンジン:engine, 臨界[りんかい]:critical (pressure, temperature, state, point), 達する[たっする]:to reach/to get to/to arrive at
（レオーノフ）
タンデムミラーエンジン
臨界に達しました
Okay, let's start
the countdown.
よーし:alright/all right/right on, 秒読み[びょうよみ]:countdown, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
（ゴロー）
よーし 秒読み 始めるぞ
議員[ぎいん]:member of the Diet, congress or parliament, まったく:really/truly|indeed, 懲りる[こりる]:to learn by experience/to learn one's lesson|to have enough (of), 連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe
（議員１）まったく懲りない連中だ
Honestly, these people
never learn...
So what? We'll just use this
for more advertising.
議員[ぎいん]:member of the Diet, congress or parliament, 宣伝[せんでん]:publicity/advertisement/advertising, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
（議員２）
何 また宣伝に使わせてもらうさ
議員[ぎいん]:member of the Diet, congress or parliament, 機会[きかい]:chance/opportunity, 新た[あらた]:new/fresh/novel, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 税[ぜい]:tax, 検討[けんとう]:consideration/examination/investigation
（議員３）これを機会に
新たな宇宙税を検討しては？
Perhaps we should use this as an excuse
to consider a new space tax?
議員[ぎいん]:member of the Diet, congress or parliament, そりゃ:very/extremely|that is
（議員２）そりゃいい
That's a good idea.
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 映像[えいぞう]:reflection|video|image in one's mind, 捉える[とらえる]:to catch|to grasp (e.g. meaning)|to captivate
（管制官１）
不明船 映像で捉えました
We have the unidentified
ship on visual.
Ship ID code analysis completed.
She's the DA-47.
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 船体[せんたい]:hull, コード:code, 解析[かいせき]:analysis/analytical study|parsing, 終了[しゅうりょう]:end/close/termination
（管制官２）船体コード
解析終了しました DA-47
うん？ 何だ？ あれは
What's that?
The lead ship is the only real one.
The others are dummies!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 実機[じっき]:real machine (as opposed to model or simulation)/existing equipment, 先頭[せんとう]:head/lead/vanguard, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
（管制官３）
実機は先頭の船のみです
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), ダミー:dummy
他はダミーです
She's a freighter that went missing.
It was a trick!
行方不明[ゆくえふめい]:missing/unaccounted for, 貨物船[かもつせん]:freighter (vessel)/cargo ship, だます:to trick/to cheat|to coax
行方不明の貨物船です
だまされました
Can you hear me, my dear
INTO representatives?
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
（白猫）聞こえていますか？
親愛[しんあい]:deep affection|dear/beloved, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
親愛なる連合の皆様
How do you do? I am a member
of the Space Defense Front.
はじめる:to start/to begin|to open (e.g. a store), 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
はじめまして
私は宇宙防衛戦線の者です
I apologize for interrupting
your important meeting.
大切[たいせつ, たいせち]:important|beloved|careful, 大切[おおぎり]:large cut (e.g. of meat)|last piece of the day's programme/last act of a play, 会議[かいぎ]:meeting/conference/session, 失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|, いたす:to do
大切な会議中 失礼いたします
I have come to you today because there
is a show that I would like all of you to see.
皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
ただ 今日はどうしても皆様に―
いただく:to receive/to get|to eat, ショー:show
見ていただきたい
ショーがありまして―
参上[さんじょう]:calling on/visiting, いたす:to do
参上いたしました
Oh, and allow me to monopolize your
communications system for a while.
しばらく:little while/short while|a while, 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 独占[どくせん]:monopoly/monopolization|hogging, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（白猫）ああ それとしばらく
通信は独占させてください
Not to worry, I will return
it to you afterwards.
返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
大丈夫 あとで お返ししますから
And without further ado, sit back
and enjoy the show.
すてき:lovely/dreamy/beautiful, ショー:show, どうぞ:please/kindly|by all means, ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful
それでは すてきなショーを
どうぞごゆっくり
As for the price of admission,
I will charge you afterwards.
代[しろ]:substitution|material|price||, 代[よ]:world/society/age, 後ほど[のちほど]:later on/eventually/afterwards, 請求[せいきゅう]:claim/demand/charge, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
お代は後ほど
請求させていただきます
Seven. Six. Five. Four.
Three. Two. One.
（ゴロー）７ ６
５ ４ ３ ２
１ ０
Zero. Ignition.
始動[しどう]:starting (in machines)/activation
始動
（レオーノフ）始動
Ignition.
What's wrong?
（ゴロー）どうした？
ロック:lock
おい ロックちゃんよ
Hey! Talk to me, Locky!
What's going on?
The engine shut down!
エンジン:engine, 止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to
どうなってんだ？
エンジン止まっちゃったぞ！
（ロックスミス）ああっ…
停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, 信号[しんごう]:signal/signalling|traffic light
停止信号
The shutdown signal...
（ゴロー）なんだって！？
The what?
非常[ひじょう]:emergency|extraordinary/unusual, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, システム:system
非常停止システムですよ
It's the emergency
shutdown system.
It's designed to shut down
the engine remotely...
テロリスト:terrorist, 乗っ取る[のっとる]:to take over/to capture|to hijack (a vehicle), 乗っ取る[のっとる]:to conform to/to be in accordance with/to follow (rule, tradition, example, etc.), 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
テロリストに乗っ取られたときの
ことを考えて―
外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, エンジン:engine, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person
外からエンジンを
停止できるようになってるんです
...in the event that the ship
is taken over by terrorists.
What about that
comm interference?
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap
（ゴロー）通信障害は？
It looks like it was uploaded
before it started.
仕込む[しこむ]:to train|to acquire (information)|to stock||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（ロックスミス）その前に
仕込まれちゃったみたいですね
生体[せいたい]:organism/living body, データ:data/datum, 全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, 盗む[ぬすむ]:to steal
キーになる生体データも
全員分 盗まれていたのかなあ
I wonder if they also stole all the biometric
data that acts as the key to the system...
The tiger is caught in the net.
That just leaves the catnip.
網[あみ]:net/netting|web, 網[もう]:network, かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
（コートの男）
トラは 網にかかった
マタタビ:silver vine (Actinidia polygama)/cat powder
あとは マタタビだけだな
（ドルフ）ああっ…
（フィー）うっ あっ…
（ユーリ）うっ ああ…
たかだか:very high/at most/at best, デブリ:debris, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
たかだかデブリ船で
どうするつもりだ？
What do you hope to accomplish
with a little debris hauler?
Are you gonna try
ramming them?
体当たり[たいあたり]:ramming attack/hurling oneself (at)|throwing oneself into (e.g. a role)
体当たりでもするのか？
You foiled us that time, but things
will be different this time.
はやる:to be popular/to come into fashion|to be prevalent, はやる:to be in high spirits/to be impatient/to be hotblooded, 今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
（ハキム）あのときはやられたが
今度はそうはいかない
Claire! Hachimaki's on
the Von Braun, too!
（ユーリ）クレア
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., ハチマキ:headband
フォン･ブラウン号には
ハチマキもいるんだぞ
フンッ それがどうしたっていうの
Am I supposed
to care?
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman, 民間[みんかん]:private/civilian/civil, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 接舷[せつげん]:coming alongside (a boat, pier, etc)
（警備員１）
なんで民間船が接舷するんだ？
Why is a civilian ship
docking with us?
Hey, have you guys had an
accident or something?
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman, おーい:hey!/oi!|I, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
（警備員２）
おーい なんか事故か？
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman, おーい:hey!/oi!|I, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
（警備員２）
おーい なんか事故か？
おおっ
二手[ふたて]:two groups/two bands, 分かれる[わかれる]:to branch|to separate|to disperse
（ハキム）二手に分かれる
We'll split into two teams. Mine will
take control of Locksmith's office.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, 押さえる[おさえる]:to pin something down|to seize|to gain control of something|
私たちは
ロックスミスの部屋を押さえる
Yours will make for the operators room,
destroying everything as you go.
各所[かくしょ]:each place/various places, 破壊[はかい]:destruction/disruption|(application) crash, オペレーター:operator, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar
そっちは各所を破壊しつつ
オペレーター室へ
（警備員）お前たち 何をやって…
Hey, what are
you people...
どわあっ
クリア:clear
（組織員）よし クリア
Okay, we're clear!
（クレア）行きましょう
Let's go.
まったく:really/truly|indeed, 偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful
（ロックスミス）
まったく お偉いさんは…
I swear, the bigwigs really need to start
thinking things through more carefully.
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
もう少し考えてくれないと…
担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.), 官[かん]:government service/the bureaucracy, 官[つかさ]:office|chief|(Yaeyama Islands in Okinawa) person (usually a woman) whose duty it is to officiate at religions ceremonies, やっぱり:too/also|still
（職員）担当官
（ロックスミス）やっぱり来た？
Director!
We've been boarded
like I thought?
Yeah, yeah. That's right, Hoshino.
The rude crew candidate.
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, 無礼[ぶれい]:impolite/rude
（コリン）そうそう 星野(ほしの)
受験生のほうの無礼なやつ
God must be awfully fair-minded
for a guy like him to have a girlfriend.
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 平等[びょうどう]:equality/impartiality/evenness
あんなのでも彼女できるなんて
神様は平等だよね
正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 武装[ぶそう]:arms/armament, 集団[しゅうだん]:group/mass, 船内[せんない]:on-board ship/inboard, 侵入[しんにゅう]:invasion/incursion/raid
（アナウンス）
正体不明の武装集団が船内に侵入
An unidentified, armed group
has boarded the ship!
繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again, 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 武装[ぶそう]:arms/armament, 集団[しゅうだん]:group/mass, 船内[せんない]:on-board ship/inboard, 侵入[しんにゅう]:invasion/incursion/raid
繰り返す
正体不明の武装集団が船内に侵入
I say again, an unidentified, armed
group has boarded the ship!
All hands, use whatever means
you see fit to repel them.
各自[かくじ]:each (person)/everyone/individual, 自己責任[じこせきにん]:self-responsibility/on one's own responsibility/at one's own risk, 対応[たいおう]:interaction/correspondence|software support
各自 自己責任において
対応するように
This is not a drill!
訓練[くんれん]:training/drill/practice
なお これは訓練ではない
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, 定刻[ていこく]:appointed time/timetable/schedule, どおり:in accordance with/following|roughly, 各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 噴射[ふんしゃ]:jet/spray/injection
（組織員１）
定刻どおり 各船噴射です
All ships have begun thrusting
on schedule.
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, ネズミ:mouse/rat, 飼い猫[かいねこ]:pet cat, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
（組織員２）
ネズミも飼い猫を捕まえたままです
The mice still have the house cat
in custody.
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 手を打つ[てをうつ]:to take measures (in face of events being anticipated)|to come to an agreement (in bargaining, etc.)|to clap one's hands together
（白猫）
そろそろ連合が次の手を打つか
It's almost time for INTO
to make their next move.
システム:system, 汚染[おせん]:pollution/contamination, 除去[じょきょ]:removal/getting rid of, 処理[しょり]:processing/dealing with/treatment, 完了[かんりょう]:completion/conclusion|perfect (tense, form, aspect), 完了[ワンラ]:end/completion
（作業員）
システム汚染の除去処理 完了です
System contamination purging complete.
Now rebooting.
再起動[さいきどう]:restart/reboot, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
再起動をかけます
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up
（管制官１）
通信障害 なくなりました
Communications interference
is gone.
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 外れる[はずれる]:to be disconnected/to get out of place/to be off, ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently, 減速[げんそく]:deceleration
（管制官２）フォン･ブラウン号
軌道を外れ ただいま 減速中
The Von Braun is leaving
its orbit and is decelerating.
At this rate, it'll be pulled in
by the moon's gravity!
重力[じゅうりょく]:gravity/gravitation/gravitational pull, つかまる:to be caught/to be arrested|to hold on to
このままでは
月の重力につかまります
The interference is gone, isn't it?
Access the ship and regain control!
障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up
障害はなくなったんだろ？
アクセス:access, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 取り戻す[とりもどす]:to take back/to regain/to get back
アクセスして船を取り戻せ
Yes, sir.
Accessing transmission system...
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 了解[りょうかい]:comprehension/consent/understanding, 送信[そうしん]:transmission/sending, システム:system
（管制官３）
了解 送信システムに…
（議員たち）おおっ
くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（白猫）お待ちください
Not so fast, gentlemen.
うっ
Suddenly hanging up on someone
isn't nice.
会話[かいわ]:conversation, 一方的[いっぽうてき]:one-sided/unilateral/arbitrary, 切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||
（白猫）
会話を一方的に切るのはよくない
方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 動向[どうこう]:trend/tendency/movement, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
それと あなた方の動向は
全てつかんでいます
Also, we already know
what you have in mind.
主要[しゅよう]:chief/main/principal, 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite, 押さえる[おさえる]:to pin something down|to seize|to gain control of something|
主要な通信衛星を
押さえましたからね
We've taken over your primary
communications satellites, you see.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown
（クリフォード）
フォン･ブラウンを―
Do you seriously think that you can keep the
Von Braun under your control for good?!
乗っ取る[のっとる]:to take over/to capture|to hijack (a vehicle), 乗っ取る[のっとる]:to conform to/to be in accordance with/to follow (rule, tradition, example, etc.)
いつまでも乗っ取っていられると
思っているのか
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
（白猫）まさか
Not at all.
Your precious Von Braun
is going to crash.
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
あなたたちの大事な
フォン･ブラウン号はね
墜落[ついらく]:falling/crashing
墜落するんですよ
うん？
The point of impact will be the moon's
largest city...
墜落[ついらく]:falling/crashing, 地点[ちてん]:site/point on a map/spot, 月面[げつめん]:moon's surface, 最大[さいだい]:biggest/greatest/largest, 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal
（白猫）
墜落地点は月面最大の都市―
静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm
静かの海市
Sea of Tranquility City.
（受付）はい
Okay, then.
Dad, Mom, they say I'll be well enough
to go on vacation next week.
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, お母さん[おかあさん]:mother
（ノノ）お父さん お母さん
来週[らいしゅう]:next week, お休み[おやすみ]:holiday|sleep|Good night
来週のお休み大丈夫だって
Why don't we all go to
the ice crater, then?
（ノノの母親）じゃあ―
氷[こおり]:ice|shaved ice (usually served with flavored simple syrup), 氷[ひ]:ice|hail, クレーター:crater
氷のクレーターにでも
みんなで行こうか
（ノノ）本当？ やったー！
Really? Yahoo!
Communications have
gone out again.
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 元どおり[もとどおり]:as before/as ever
通信 また元どおりですね
どうなってんだ おい
What the hell
is going on?
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 回復[かいふく]:restoration/rehabilitation|recovery (from an illness), 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, データ:data/datum, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
一度 回復したとき
軌道データを取っておいたんですが
While they were back online, I went ahead
and grabbed all of our orbital data.
Oh, well, just so long as
we can get our job done...
無事[ぶじ]:safety/peace/quietness, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|
（操縦士）こっちは
無事に仕事が済めば それだけで…
- I don't believe it!
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
（チェンシン）まさか
テロなんじゃ
（操縦士）はあ？
It might be terrorists!
（警備員）うわっ
（組織員）うっ…
機関長[きかんちょう]:chief engineer
（レオーノフ）
機関長 何してんですか？
Chief, what're you doing?!
What does it look like?
I'm gonna fight 'em!
戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.), 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
（ゴロー）
戦うのに決まってんだろ！
But those are terrorists
out there!
相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), テロリスト:terrorist
（サリー）
相手はテロリストですよ
間に合わせ[まにあわせ]:makeshift, 武器[ぶき]:weapon/arms|weapon (something used to gain an advantage), 勝つ[かつ]:to win/to gain victory, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.)
（レオーノフ）
間に合わせの武器で勝てる相手じゃ
You can't beat those guys
using makeshift weapons!
理屈[りくつ]:theory/reason
理屈 言ってんじゃねえ
Don't quibble
with me, boy!
What's your problem?!
A sailor has to defend his ship!
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
てめえの船ぐらい
てめえで守らなくてどうすんだよ
ああっ
機関長[きかんちょう]:chief engineer, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, 信号[しんごう]:signal/signalling|traffic light, ロック:lock, 外す[はずす]:to unfasten|to remove|to leave|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
じゃあ 機関長は
停止信号のロックを外してください
In that case, you go disengage the
shutdown signal lockout, Chief!
うん？
稼ぐ[かせぐ]:to earn (income)|to score (points, victory)|to work hard (at one's job)
（レオーノフ）
俺たちが時間 稼ぎますから
We'll buy you
the time you need.
（組織員）うっ
あいつだ
It's him...
あいつが来たんだ
That bastard's here...
あっ…
んん…
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
こいつで 今度こそ―
I'll use this...
And finish the job this time.
やつを…
He's dead.
（組織員）うっ…
冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story
冗談だろ！
Are you kidding me?!
The OSA is supposed to be on board!
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954)
軌道保安庁がいるはずなのに
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away, ドッキング:docking, アクセス:access
（リュシー）逃げましょう
ドッキングアクセスへ
Let's get out of here!
Head for the docking access port!
親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss
（コリン）親父(おやじ)は何をやってるんだ
What the hell
is my dad doing?!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
（タナベ）先輩なら 船を守る
Knowing Senpai,
he'll defend the ship.
はっ タナベ！
Tanabe!
（タナベ）あの人は―
He's the kind of person who'd fight,
even against terrorists.
テロリスト:terrorist, 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.)
テロリストでも
絶対 戦っちゃう人だ
（タナベ）うっ
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩！ どこですか？
Senpai! Where are you?!
（ハキム）
こっちも リーをやられた
We lost Lee here.
We'll have his office secured soon.
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 執務[しつむ]:performance of one's official duties, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar, 押さえる[おさえる]:to pin something down|to seize|to gain control of something|
もう少しで執務室を押さえる
そちら:that way (direction distant from the speaker, close to the listener)|there (place distant from the speaker, close to the listener), 機関[からくり]:mechanism|trick|mechanical doll, 機関[きかん]:engine|agency|system, 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|
そちらは機関部に回ってくれ
Your team should head
for Engineering.
It sounds like the crew candidates are
fighting back with work equipment.
候補生[こうほせい]:cadet, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, 機械[きかい]:machine/mechanism|instrument, 抵抗[ていこう]:resistance|reluctance|resistance||, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（ハキム）候補生が作業用の機械で
抵抗しているらしい
With tools?
物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods
（クレア）そんな物で？
機関[からくり]:mechanism|trick|mechanical doll, 機関[きかん]:engine|agency|system, 増援[ぞうえん]:reinforcement
機関部ね 今すぐ増援に
Engineering, right?
We're on our way back them...
機関[からくり]:mechanism|trick|mechanical doll, 機関[きかん]:engine|agency|system, 増援[ぞうえん]:reinforcement
機関部ね 今すぐ増援に
（クレア）うっ
（ハキム）はっ…
What's up?
（組織員）どうした？
（ハキム）いや
It's nothing.
（警備員）こっちだ まだいるぞ
This way! There's more
of them!
（組織員たち）うおっ
撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat, 降参[こうさん]:surrender/submission|being defeated (e.g. by a problem)
（ハキム）撃たないでくれ 降参だ
Please, don't shoot! I surrender!
Please! Don't shoot me!
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|, 撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat
頼む 撃たないで
んん… うっ
（ハキム）ハァ…
ロックスミス
Locksmith!
一足[いっそく]:pair (footwear), 一足[ひとあし]:step|short distance/short time, 遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
一足 遅かったか
We got here
too late, huh?
一足[いっそく]:pair (footwear), 一足[ひとあし]:step|short distance/short time, 遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
一足 遅かったか
（ハキム）ん？ チッ…
I guess I'll take a gun
off of one of the guards.
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman, 銃[じゅう]:gun/rifle/small arms
警備員の銃でも使うか
（ハチマキ）かあっ
（ハキム）うっ ああっ
うっ うあっ
悩む[なやむ]:to be worried/to be troubled
（ハチマキ）悩んだよ
I couldn't make up
my mind...
I couldn't decide if you were gonna
head to the engine room or to here.
機関室[きかんしつ]:engine room
お前が行くのは機関室か
それとも ここか
星野
Hoshino...
ヘヘッ
やっと:at last/at length|barely, 会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association
やっと会えたな
So, we meet again...
...Hakim.
ハキム！
♪～
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Love
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
（コートの男）
フォン･ブラウン号が―
If the Von Braun crashes onto
Sea of Tranquility City,
墜落[ついらく]:falling/crashing
墜落すれば―
静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm, 万[ばん]:many/all, 万[まん, よろず]:10,000|myriad|everything|, 一瞬[いっしゅん]:instant/moment/for an instant, 消滅[しょうめつ]:extinction/extinguishment|annihilation
静かの海市の12万人は
一瞬で消滅する
...its 120,000 residents will all
be wiped out in an instant.
Come, let's bear witness together. Let's watch
as the course of history is changed!
共[ども]:first-person plural (or singular)|second or third person plural (implies speaker is of higher status than those referred to), 共[とも]:together with|same|both|, 立ち会う[たちあう]:to be present/to be witness to, 歴史[れきし]:history, 修正[しゅうせい]:amendment/correction/revision, 点[ちょぼ, チョボ]:dot/point|gidayuu musicians (in kabuki), 点[てん]:spot|point|mark (e.g. in exam)||
さあ 共に立ち会おう
歴史の修正点に
ちくしょーっ！
Son of a bitch!
- Every single life is precious.
全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 尊い[とうとい, たっとい]:precious/valuable/priceless
（タナベ）
全ての命は尊いんです
愛す[あいす]:to love
愛すべきものなんです
Every one of them should be cherished!
But here you are, talking about how one
life is valuable, while another isn't!
価値[かち]:value/worth/merit
それなのに
価値があるとかないとか
It doesn't make
any sense to me!
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely
そんなの
全然 分かりませんよ！